Guide to the New York State Teachers Association Records 1915-1979
New York State Teachers Association Records
- Series III: Executive Secretary's Files
  - Sub-Series C: Goold Subject Files, 1950-1971, 1950-1971
    - Sub-Series a: Committees
      - Zone Organization, Representation and Structure, 1954 (Box 27, Folder 24)
        Contains data on local assn., recommendations of the committee, minutes of meetings, report on the equity of representation on the Bd. Of Dir. Also contains info on questionnaire responses concerning zone meetings and a memo outlining the problems of zone organization, 1954.
      - Committee to Study Zone Priorities and Expenses, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 25)
      - Committee on Zone Structure, 1958 (Box 27, Folder 26)
        Contains report of committee to Bd. Of Dir., the 1st progress report, a tentative plan for structural chances in NYSTA's organization, minutes, various memos re purpose of committee, 1958
      - Committee to Study Zone Structure, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 27)
        Contains minutes, a progress report on committee activities, a proposal re the organization of NYSTA for legislative action. Report re of NYSTA for legislative action. Report re organization of NYSTA to carry out the internal operation of its affairs, professional programs and its legislative program, 1959
      - Committee on Zone Structure, 1960 (Box 27, Folder 28)
        Contains the draft of bylaw amendments, 1960
    - Sub-Series b: Legislation
      This series contains bills, memos, and correspondence concerning various NYSTA legislative efforts. These files are arranged chronologically and alphabetically within a year.
      - L-General, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 29)
      - L-Budget Hearing (February 6: cumulative 1956-54-53), 1959 (Box 27, Folder 30)
        Contains Goold's statement at the Budget Hearing for 1958, 56, and 54. Also contains an analysis of the 1958-59 tentative budget estimate for NNY City and an analysis of the State Budget. 1959
      - L-Budget Hearings, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 31)
        Contains the statements of Gould, Dyer (executive director of the NY State School Board Assoc.) and Plowden-Warlwa (Empires State Chamber of commerce). 1959
      - L-Federal (Box 27, Folder 32)
        Contains congressional records for 1962, 1958, 1957, and 1955 and arguments (pro and con) concerning Federal Aid to Schools. Also contains testimony before the House Education and Labor committee, an explanation of the Library Services bill and G.I. Bill of Rights Extension, a document concerning Federal taxation of permanent disability retirement allowances, comparison of old and new tax laws, NGA membership dues deductible, and tax cred for retirement income. The social security bill and an analysis of bill are also included, plus bills dealing with teachers and 1953-58 cumulative federal income tax. 1959
      - L-Federal (Howard Sackett) 1959 (Box 27, Folder 33)
      - Federal Legislation (Murray-Metcalf Bill) 1959 (Box 27, Folder 34)
      - L-for consideration, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 35)
        Contains the report of the Resolutions Committee, resolutions adopted by the 1967 House of Delegates, recommendations to the Board of directors from he Retirement Committee, and minute s of the Meeting of the Board of Directors, May 16-17, 1958, 1959
      - L-Memos to the Governor, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 36)
        Contains various bills and memos concerning 1959 legislation. (additional opportunity of obtaining old age and survivors insurance coverage. - limitation on the incurring of indebtedness in YC) 1959
      - L-Memos to the Governor, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 37)
        Contains various bills and memos concerning 1959 legislation. (racetrack employment- withholding of state aid for school purposes upon default) 1959
      - L-Memoranda, Special (Machenzie, Brygdges, Brady, Embler, Erwin, Kaplan, et al.), 1959 (Box 27, Folder 38)
        Contains bill and correspondence dealing with superintendent qualifications. Also general correspondence is included. 1959.
      - L-Memoranda to Mr. Embler, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 39)
        Contains a memo dealing with minimum salary legislation plus bills concerning leave of absence for personal illness and extension of time period in which to elect old age and survivors insurance coverage. 1959
      - L-Mentally Retarded, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 40)
        Contains pamphlets from the Parents Association for children with Retarded Mental Development. 1959
      - L-NYSTA Program 1959 (Box 27, Folder 41)
      - L- Race Track, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 42)
        Contains a bill concerning racetrack employment. 1959
      - L- Retirement, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 43)
        General correspondence 1959
      - L- Retirement Death Benefit, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 44)
        Contains death benefit bill and memo. 1959
      - L-Retirement, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 45)
        3 year final average salary contains bill and memos. 1959
      - Retirement, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 46)
        (additional pension 1/140 over 35 years of service)-cotnains bills and memo. 1959
      - Retirement, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 47)
        Prior Service Credit- Contains the act and memo. 1959
      - L-Correspondence, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 48)
        re Prior Service Credit. Contains the prior service bill and memo. 1959
      - L-Retirement-Special Service 955-yer plan), 1959 (Box 28, Folder 1)
        Contains bill and memo plus general correspondence. 1959.
      - L-Retirement Vesting Interest, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 2)
        Contains a copy of the bill. 1959
      - L-School Bond authority 1959 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - L-Sick Leave, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 4)
        Contains act and memo. 1959
      - L-Principals Salary, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 5)
        contains bill and memo. 1959
      - L-correspondence re Principal Salary. 1959 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - L- Salary Teachers, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 7)
        Contains bill and memo. 1959
      - L-State aid General 1959 (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - L-State Aid (conference Board Bill) (Box 28, Folder 9)
        Contains an act and memo. 1959
      - State Aid-Proposed Commission to Study Educational Finance (Speno bill), 1959 (Box 28, Folder 10)
        Contains the Speno Bill and news releases. 1959
      - L-State Aid, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 11)
        Support for Conference Board Bill-Contains a paper on educational finance and data on finances in the South Nassau School District. 1959
      - L-Superintendents Bill (Certification), 1959-1959 (Box 28, Folder 12)
        Contains the bill and a supportive statement. 1959
      - L-Supplemental Pension (Box 28, Folder 13)
        Contains the bill 1959.
      - L-Tax Deduction (state), 1959 (Box 28, Folder 14)
        re education expenses. Contains the bill. 1959
      - Legislation, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 15)
        Tax Exemption Railroads. Contains the bill. 1959
      - L-Telephone Tax, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 16)
        Contains the bill and explanatory documents. Also contains a publication by Bell Telephone. 1959
      - Welfare and Pension Plans Disclosure Act (Federal), 1959 (Box 28, Folder 17)
        Contains the bill and descriptive memos. 1959
      - L-General 1960 (Box 28, Folder 18)
      - L-Budget Hearings (Box 28, Folder 19)
        Contains the statements of the Teacher's Union of NYC, G.H. Goold and Everett Dyer
      - Citizens Committee for Children of NYC (Box 28, Folder 20)
        Contains committee comments on Mayor Wagner's program on juvenile delinquency, and on the recommendation of the interdepartmental Task force on youth and delinquency. Also contains a special report on Juvenile Delinquency and Youth Crime in NYC and the report on major legislative action affecting families and children during the 1960 session of the legislature, a pamphlet concerning the committee is also contained. 1960.
      - L-Cooperative Boards, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 21)
        Contains the cooperative education bill, and memoranda, a research paper on cooperative education and an organizational description of Boards of cooperative Educational Service. 1960
      - L-Duty Free Lunch Period for Teachers, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 22)
        Contains the bill and memo. 1960
      - Federal Aid (Box 28, Folder 23)
        Contains hearings concerning the school lunch program, the statement of Sam Lambert(Director of NEA Research) on federal aid, the essay of Walter Heller re aid and the Chamber of Commerce report on aid to education. 1959-60
      - Federal Legislation, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 24)
        Contains bills concerning construction of elementary and secondary facilities and teachers' salary. Also contains a congressional record dealing with federal aid for teachers' salaries, NEA reports and an NEA report on quality education, 1960.
      - L-Federated School Districts, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 25)
        Contains a bill re the above. 1960
      - L-fiscal Independence, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 26)
        Contains the constitution of, the minutes of meetings of (May 20, 1960, March, 7, 1969, Jan 25, 1960) and the review of activities of the conference of large boards of education of NY state. Also a statement re the fiscal problems of Board of Education of Yonkers, N.Y. 1960.
      - Proposal Legislation, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 27)
        Contains a report on the 1959 session of the NYS Legislature 1960
      - L-Memos to the Governor, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 28)
        Contains 1960 legislation and memos
      - L-Special Memos, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 29)
        Brydges, rockefeller, Mahoney, Hurd, Mackenzie. 1960
      - L-Mentally Retarded (Box 28, Folder 30)
        Contains the 1960 and 1962 Annual report of the New York State Joint Legislative Committee on Mental Retardation and Physical Handicap. Also includes a publication from National committee Against Mental Illness In., a paper dealing with problems in providing service for the mentally retarded, the report of Legal and Legislative committee to AHRC Board of Governor's Meeting, data concerning classes for the mentally retarded, the brief and statement of Goold before the Joint Legislative committee on Mental Retardation (Feb. 2, 1960) 1960
      - L-NYSTA Program, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 31)
        Contains general memos and the 1960 legislative program. 1960
      - L-Race Tracks, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 32)
        Contains a bill re employment of public employees at race tracks. 1960
      - Retirement-Disability, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 33)
        Contains a bill and memo dealing with disability. 1960
      - Retirement, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 34)
        3 year Final Average Salary-contains a bill and memo re final average slary.1960
      - L-Retirement, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 35)
        Out of State Service (super annulation)-Contains the bill memo, and general correspondence. 1960
      - Retirement, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 36)
        Prior Service Credit-contains the prior service bill and memo plus general correspondence. 1960
      - L-Retirement Vesting, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 37)
        Contains bills and memos re vesting, deferred retirement, minimum salary. 1960
      - L-Roll Calls on Bills 1960 (Box 28, Folder 38)
      - L-Principal's Salary, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 39)
        Contains the bill 1960
      - L-Minimum Salaries-Teachers, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 40)
        Contains the bill and memo, data on salaries and the e cost of higher salaries and a research bulletin on salary gains for experiences and beginning teachers. 1960
      - L-Sick Leave, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 41)
        Contains bill and memo 1960
      - L-State Aid-Mr. Carlino, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 42)
        Contains a legislative bulletin issued by Mr. Carlino, 1960
      - L-State Aid Conference Board Bill, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 43)
        Contains bill and memo plus a memo containing data dealing with public school expenditures. 1960
      - L-State Aid Bills Other Than Conference Board, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 44)
        Contains bill and memo for 1961 State aid. Also contains an estimate for the effect on school districts of the Republican State Aid Program. 1960
      - L-State Aid Data from Dr. Burke, 1960-1961 (Box 28, Folder 45)
        Also contains the appropriations bill for 1960-61 and a memo re means of providing a temporary aid increases in 1961-62. 1960-61
      - State Aid-Howard Henig, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 46)
        Contains the report of the Local Government Workshop, school tax rates and expenditures, a study on school quality by the NYS Educational Conference Board, and memos concerning the budget, 1960 state aid adjustments had non property taxes. 1960
      - State Aid and School Finance, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 47)
        9ACtion in School Districts etc.)-contains the state aid plan, general correspondence, a news release from the committee for economic development, a study on school quality, a study re a sales tax, and various financial information for school districts. 1960
      - State Aid to Education, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 48)
        Study by Joint Legislative Committee. 1960
      - L-Superintendents Certification, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 49)
        Contains a bill concerning educational and experiences requirements for qualifications as superintendent. 1960
      - L- Supplemental Pensions (Box 28, Folder 50)
        Contains the bill and general correspondence
      - L-Take-Home Pay, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 51)
        contains bills re increases take-home pay, death benefits, and retirement at age 55, Also contains a pros and cons discussion of the 590 take-home pay plan, and general correspondence opposing the pay plan, 1960
      - Legislation-Tenure(Ostrander), 1960 (Box 28, Folder 52)
        Contains the bill. 1960
      - L-Termination of Service (30 day notice), 1960 (Box 28, Folder 53)
        contains the bill and a memo, and news clipping for Teachers union of the City of NY. 1960
      - L-Transportation, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 54)
        contains a bill and memo and an opposition memo. 1960
      - Legislation-General, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        Contains bills and memos re apportionment, deduction from wages for payment and credit unions, minimum salaries, death benefits, deferred retirement allowance, final average salary, and supplemental pensions. Also contains the report of the resolutions committee and general correspondence with newspaper clippings. 1961
      - L-General No. 2, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 2)
        Contains the 1961 legislative program plus reasons for supporting the program. Also contains bills re appropriates for the culturally deprived, deficiency contributions by employers, the powers of the State Civil Service Commission, the reimbursement for expenses incurred by school district officers, a special class for the mentally retarded, and a memo opposing teacher unionization. Memos from the Citizens Committee for Children are also included.
      - Legislation-Budget Hearing, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 3)
        Contains the statements of Everett Dyer (Executive director of the NY State School Board Assoc.), G.H. Goold and Rose Russell (Teacher's Union of NYC) at the budget meeting. 1961
      - L-Bulletin Mailing List, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - L-Citizen Committee for Children of New York City, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 5)
        Contains memos in support of various welfare legislation. 1961
      - L-Civil Service Positions, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        Contains bill re certification of payrolls of state employees and a memo re Civil Service proceeding relative to educational positions in Cattaraugus County. 1961
      - L-Duty Free Lunch Period, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 7)
        General, 1961
      - L-duty Free Lunch Period, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 8)
        contains bill and memo. 1961
      - L-Federal Aid, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 9)
        Contains numerous pamphlets and memos discussing federal aid to education, a memo containing arguments in support of federal aid, a report on aid by the NEA, a statement on aid y the Roman Catholic archdiocese of NY, plus general correspondence. 1961
      - L-5% Take-home Pay-General (Box 29, Folder 10)
      - L- 5% Take-home Pay, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 11)
        contains memos and correspondence re 5% take-home pay 1961
      - L-Group Life Insurance 1961 (Box 29, Folder 12)
      - Legislative Program, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 13)
        Contains bills and memos re the 1961 Legislative Program. 1961
      - Legislative Program of the Legislative Council, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 14)
        contains data on salaries plus bills and memos concerning the 1961 legislative program. 1961
      - Legislation-Memoranda, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 15)
        Also contains memos re salaries with cost estimates. 1961
      - L-Memos etc., 1961 (Box 29, Folder 16)
        (speaker of Assembly-Mr. Curlino, Mr. Bisceglia) Also contains a bill re the NY State Higher Education Assistance Corporation. 1961
      - L-Memos to Mr. Embler 1961 (Box 29, Folder 17)
      - L-Memos to t. Norman Hurd. 1961 (Box 29, Folder 18)
      - L-Memos to Robert McCrate, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 19)
        Contains bills and memos re apportionment, minimum salaries, deferred retirement allowance, death benefits, final average salary, duty free lunch period, and supplemental retirement allowances. 1961
      - L-Mentally Retarded, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 20)
        Contains the annual report of the NYS Joint Legislative Committee on Mental Retardation and Physical Handicap for 1961 and 1959. also included is the Committee's 1961 Legislative Problem. 1961
      - L-Out Memos re Labor Law, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 21)
        McCrate (Corbin), Hurd, Mahoney-Ronan. 1961
      - Legislation (Box 29, Folder 22)
        Special Session (8/21/61) re NYC Schools- Contains the bill re the constitution of the Board of Education of the City School District of NYC, the message to the Legislature, the public letter to the citizens of NYC by its school board president, a synopsis of work of the Bureau of Audit, a memo re actions taken to combat illegal activities by employees and contractors, a memo re the organization of school administration, and the repair program, the report by the board of Superintendents, the NYC Board of Education assessing quality of Instructional program, a statement of the Board of Regents and the commissioner of Education re their Legislative Proposal for Emergency action with respect to NYC schools, a bill and background information on NYC schools. News clippings included.
      - L-Retirement General. 1961 (Box 29, Folder 23)
      - L-Retirement-Death Benefits, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 24)
        contains a bill and memo re death benefits. 1961
      - L-Death Benefit Memo. 1961 (Box 29, Folder 25)
      - L-Retirement-Final Average Salary, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 26)
        contains the bill and memo. 1961
      - L-Retirement Prior Service Credit, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 27)
        contains general correspondence. 1961
      - L-Special Service Retirement (GHG for Se. Van Wiggeran), 1961 (Box 29, Folder 28)
        Contains the act. 1961
      - L-Vesting General, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 29)
        Contains general correspondence plus an explanatory memo. 1961
      - L-Vesting re Retirement, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 30)
        Contains the bill and explanatory memos. 1961
      - Legislation-Roll Call Votes (Box 29, Folder 31)
        Contains the vote on the minimum salary bill, the 15% increase in basic school support, death benefits, deferred retirement rights (vesting) supplemental pension (one year extension). Supplemental pinion (one year extension), supplemental pension (purchase prior service after 2 years) 30 minute lunch period, labor exemption, 5% take home pay optional, and amendments to Speno transportation. 1961
      - L-Teacher's Salaries-General. 1961 (Box 29, Folder 32)
      - L-Teachers Salary, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 33)
        Contains a bill on minimum salaries with numerous explanatory memos, and memos comparing salaries for teachers in various states. 1961
      - L-Teachers' Salary Amended, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 34)
        Contains the minimum salary bill with memos re Oneonta salary schedule, costs of proposed salary revision, the interpretation of the 1961 salary law, and the comparison of the 1956 and 61 salary law interpretations, explanatory memos, a memo re a salary dispute and other general memos dealing with the 1961 law. 1961
      - L-Teachers Salary Memorandum No. 2 1961 (Box 29, Folder 35)
      - L-Teachers' Salary Memo no. 3 (Cost Estimate) 1961 (Box 29, Folder 36)
      - L-Sale of Alcoholic Beverages, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 37)
        Contains the bill. 1961
      - L-State aid General, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 38)
        contains memos re state aid from Herkimer and Onondaga counties and Wilson Central District plus general correspondence, 1961
      - L-State Aid (Conference Board Bill), 1961 (Box 29, Folder 39)
        Contains bills and memos re apportionment 1961
      - L-State aid Increased Weighting for high school, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 40)
        (G.H. Goold for secondary administrators association) Contains the bill and memo. 1961
      - L-State Aid Re Local Finance Law, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 41)
        (PTA bill prepared by Dr. Burke)-Contains bill re limitation on the amount of local indebtedness which may be contracted by certain school districts. 1961
      - L-State Aid Worksheets (ed report) 1961 (Box 29, Folder 42)
      - Superintendents' Certification, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 43)
        Contains the bill and memos plus correspondence re passage of the e bill. 1961
      - L-Supplemental Pension, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 44)
        Contains bill and memo. 1961
      - L-Transportation, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 45)
        Contains a news release and an explanatory memo on transportation for school children. 1961
      - L-General (Box 29, Folder 46)
        contains memo re proposals for educational opportunity, a statement re the sale of alcohol, and a pamphlet on the effect it has upon education plus supporting and opposing memos dealing with relevant legislation. Also contains bills dealing with Regents' Scholarships, the testing of students, and school tax exemption for persons on fixed incomes who are over 65. General correspondence also included, 1961.
      - L-Budget Hearings (Feb 15, 1962) (Box 29, Folder 47)
        Contains Goold's statement at the hearing and the statement of Max Rubin (President, Board of Education) at the hearing 1962.
      - L-City-wide committee for Equal Retirement for NYC Teachers. 1962 (Box 29, Folder 48)
      - L-Collective Bargaining, 1962 (Box 29, Folder 49)
        Contains a bill re collective bargaining by teachers and other employees. 1962
      - L-Diefendorf Proposals, Comments on. (Box 29, Folder 50)
        Contains the bills re taxing and apportionment, a review of proposal of the joint legislative committee on school Financing, the statements of Arvid Burke the Central School Boards Committee for Educational Research, the Teachers' Union of NYC, and the Westchester County Council of Chief School Officers to the Joint Legislative Committee on School Finance. Also contains the Brief of Thomas Hance (Letchworth BOE), Robert Witta (Arcade BOE), and Darwin Kittsley (Attica Central School). A summary of the Diefendorf proposal, comments on the report of the Finance committee and a Central School Board Committee for Educational Research is also included, plus an outline of Diefendorf effects on Monroe county. 1962
      - L-Federal Aid, 1962 (Box 29, Folder 51)